# 哈喽 大家好 我是王刚
Hello, everyone. I'm Wang Gang.
# 最近有一个粉丝给我发私信
Recently a fan messaged me,
# 问那个海水里面的鱼为什么海水那么咸
asking why salt water
# 这个鱼不咸
doesn't make saltwater fish salty?
# 四伯爷 你晓得是为啥子不嘛
Do you know why, uncle?
# 不晓得
I have no clue
# 海里头的鱼你想像它是咸的是淡的
You can imagine that saltwater fish they live in ocean...
# 海里的鱼应该说是咸的
I think fish in ocean should be salty
# 是咸的啊
Should be salty, huh?
# 嗯
Yes
# 就是说像我伯爷是在四川这边
You know my uncle lives in Sichuan
# 没有在海边待太久
He didn't spend much of his life near ocean
# 所以他觉得海水是咸的
So he thinks ocean water, which is salty,
# 所以里面的鱼也是咸的
should make the fish salty too.
# 其实不是的
Well, it's not.
# 海水里面的鱼
Saltwater fish
# 为什么说它的肉不是咸的呢
The reason why their meat is not salty,
# 是因为它的腮里面有一种特殊的细胞
is because they have a special cell in their gills
# 可以过滤这个海盐
that can filter out the salt.
# 除了它的鱼鳃
Besides their gills,
# 还有它的肾
their kidneys also help by
# 还有通过它的排尿系统
pumping out excessive salt
# 把多余的盐分排出去
through the urinary system.
# 所以它的肉里面的话
So the meat inside
# 不是咸的
is not salty.
# 要不然就是变成咸鱼了
Otherwise it will just be salted fish
# 还有一个奇怪的现象就是说
Another interesting fact.
# 四伯爷 我先问你嘛
Uncle, let me ask you first.
# 你晓不晓得有一种鱼哈
It's about a type of fish.
# 如果是我们的草鱼放到海里去它会不会死
You know if we put a grass carp into the ocean, will it live?
# 它可能要遭（死）
It will be dead.
# 肯定要遭（死）嘎
Certainly dead right?
# 肯定遭
Of course
# 为啥子
What's your reasoning?
# 它的这个水性就养不活
The water is hostile to its survival
# 嗯 这一点我伯爷说对了
Yes. Uncle gets it right.
# 淡水的鱼它没有办法过滤盐分 所以它会死掉
Freshwater fish can't filter out salt, so it will die.
# 海水里面的鱼放在淡水里面来的话
Vice versa, if we put saltwater fish in fresh water,
# 可能因为这个水的性质也会死掉
it will also most likely die because of the water condition.
# 但是有一种鱼很特殊
But there is a special type of fish,
# 比如说是鲈鱼 还有那个鳗鱼
including bass, eel
# 还有那个刀鱼
and Chinese tapertail anchovy.
# 这些鱼的话它有比较特殊的一个功能
These fish has a special capability.
# 就是在咸水里面它可以去适应环境
They can adjust to the saline environment in salt water
# 去过滤盐分
and be able to filter out salt.
# 如果是在淡水里面的话
If instead in fresh water,
# 它又可以改变自身的一些东西
they can adjust their body compositions,
# 它又可以在淡水里面生活
to be able to live in fresh water.
# 就是特别的奇怪
It's very strange.
# 我还在我们农村这个稻田里面
I once fished a bass here
# 田里面你知道吗 钓过鲈鱼
right in this rice field.
# 所以我觉得这个特别好玩
So I find it's very interesting.
# 这个你晓不晓得我是咋子晓得的这个
Do you know how I came to know this?
# 我不晓得
I don't
# 是因为我以前在海边嘛
I used to live near the ocean
# 我从小就去外地了在海边
I moved to a coastal city when I was little
# 别人说海水是咸的
People said sea water is salty
# 我就尝了一下 确实很咸
So I had a taste. It was indeed salty.
# 而且咸得发苦
Salty and bitter
# 所以我长大了之后做了厨师
So when I grew up and became a chef,
# 然后在学厨的这个过程中
and during my apprenticeship,
# 就学了很多比较冷门的一些知识吧
I learnt many similar fun facts.
# 所以我就晓得这些
That's how I came understand these facts
# 为啥子咋个鱼蛋那
Then why do people bring fish eggs
# 在我们这边又繁殖得起来嘛在广州运回来的
from Guangzhou and they can incubate them here.
# 鱼蛋
Fish eggs?
# 嗯
Yes.
# 啥子蛋
What fish eggs?
# 这次你幺舅公就在珠海的堰塘
My uncle lives at Yantang, Zhuhai.
# 弄的鱼苗是不
He got some juvenile fish?
# 嗯鱼种 鱼蛋
Yes. Both that and fish eggs.
# 他弄到这边来再孵化嘛
He wanted to incubated them here?
# 弄到这边来养撒
Incubate and raise them
# 这个正常
That is normal
# 所以说我们很多鱼啊 比如说鲈鱼
So it seems many fish, like bass,
# 从广东运过来到四川
transported from Guangdong
# 放到那个淡水里面养 也养得活
can also be raised here in fresh water.
# 然后就是我们这个淡水鱼
Freshwater fish
# 淡水鱼的话 其实鱼里面也是有盐分的
actually have salt.
# 它是通过在淡水里面吸收盐分
They absorb salt from surrounding water
# 让自己保持一个平衡
to maintain a body fluid balance.
# 好了 本期视频就到这里
OK. That's all for this episode.
# 然后后续的话会给跟大家分享
Later I will keep sharing
# 更多的冷门知识
more fun facts with you.
# 我个人觉得是比较冷门的
I think they are quite novel
# 然后可能大家都不怎么了解
You may not have heard about them before
# 后续我会继续跟大家分享
I'll keep sharing
# 好吧就到这里 拜拜
That's it. Bye bye.
# 拜拜
Bye bye.
# 这个鱼这个东西拿给你研究得很彻底
You seem to know everything about fish
# 开玩笑 我做了好多年的鱼哦
You must be joking. I've been cooking fish for so many years.